<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hashan&#39;s Data Science Blog</title>
    <link>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hashan&#39;s Data Science Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://hashansl.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Writing Is Thinking: A Cognitive Approach to Learning</title>
      <link>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/post/writingplan/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/post/writingplan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One special thing about myself is I really like to code. I would spend countless hours to solve a problem. When I am coding, time goes really fast!. It is mainly because I really enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I hate writing. It is not my first language. When I was a kid, I had really-bad grades for English. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know grammar, and I struggle a lot! When time goes by, I improved my English. I knew some amount of grammar, and I could write something, but it was never perfect!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recursion</title>
      <link>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/post/recursion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/post/recursion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a student of Statistics and Data Science, I used to overlook certain topics in Data Structures and Algorithms. To be honest, I never really needed them in my research work, so I let myself believe they weren’t relevant. But as I started taking on different kinds of projects, especially ones involving coding challenges and system design, I realized I was missing something important.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the concepts I struggled with the most was &lt;strong&gt;recursion&lt;/strong&gt;. It felt confusing and even a bit intimidating. I would look at recursive code and wonder, &lt;em&gt;Where does it end? How does it even work?&lt;/em&gt; So, I ignored it until I couldn’t anymore.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to My Second Brain!</title>
      <link>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/post/myfirstpost/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/post/myfirstpost/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, I have been steadily working and growing in the field of data science! navigating its steep learning curves, celebrating small breakthroughs, and wrestling with the occasional late-night bug that just wouldn’t go away. But it wasn’t until a recent conversation with a Senior Data Scientist at Apple that something clicked.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During our mentoring session, he casually mentioned that he is been keeping a blog to document his journey, sharing insights, reflecting on lessons learned, and even using it to connect with others in the field. That simple idea stuck with me. It felt like a nudge I didn’t know I needed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hashansl.github.io/blog/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;hi-im-hashan&#34;&gt;Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Hashan&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a PhD candidate in Data Science &amp;amp; Engineering at the University of Tennessee and a Research Assistant at Oak Ridge National Lab. My work focuses on applying &lt;strong&gt;topological data analysis&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Bayesian modeling&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;AI&lt;/strong&gt; to real-world problems like the opioid epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This blog is a place where I share:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Insights from my research&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Notes and summaries of technical topics&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thoughts on data, science, and learning&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-research-interests&#34;&gt;My Research Interests&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Topological data analysis (TDA)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bayesian spatial modeling (BYM, MCMC)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Natural Language Processing (NLP) in healthcare&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Computational epidemiology&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-im-learning&#34;&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;m Learning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently exploring:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
